Inventory of the Joseph Cummings Papers, 1851 - 1899
Joseph Cummings Papers, 1851 - 1899
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Cummings, Joseph, 1817-1890.
1000-89
0.5
1
Joseph Cummings was the fifth president of Wesleyan University and its first alumnus to serve as president.
This collection is primarily comprised of Joseph Cummings' annual reports on Wesleyan University for the years 1857-1874, excepting the 1866-1867 school year. The collection also contains Cummings' correspondence, including with Julia Olin and W.O. Atwater (primarily regarding securing Atwater's employment), as well as Cummings' official acceptance of the position as president at Wesleyan University. Also included are several articles by Cummings, a petition against his resignation from the professorship, and his wife Deborah S. Cummings' correspondence.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Acquired prior to 1974.
Other Finding Aids
An older, typed description of individual pieces of correspondence is available; consult a staff member for use.
Biographical Note
Joseph Cummings was the fifth president of Wesleyan University and its first alumnus to serve as president. He was born on March 3, 1817 in Falmouth County, Maine. Cummings attended Wesleyan University, graduating with highest honors in 1840. He taught mathematics and natural science at Amenia Seminary in New York for three years, serving as its principal for three more years before resigning to become a Methodist minister. In 1851, after seven years of preaching, Cummings was chosen president of Genesee College in Lima, New York (later to become Syracuse University). He was elected president of his alma mater, Wesleyan, in 1857, but only commenced his term in 1858, as he was unwilling to so abruptly leave Genesee. Cummings' Wesleyan presidency spanned the Civil War, during which 133 students left Wesleyan to join the Union Army, and several others left to join the Confederate Army. Despite this disruption, Cummings supervised the construction of several buildings, including Rich Library (now the Patricelli '92 Theatre), Memorial Chapel, and Orange Judd Hall. He also enlarged the school's curriculum - particularly in the natural sciences - and oversaw the admission of women, a policy maintained until 1909. However, the 1873 depression inhibited some of Cummings' attempts at expansion, provoking tension between Cummings and the trustees, which led to his 1875 resignation. He stayed on campus as head of the department of philosophy for two years before leaving to preach once more. In 1881, he was elected president of Northwestern University. He died May 7, 1890.
Collection Overview
This collection is primarily comprised of Joseph Cummings' annual reports on Wesleyan University for the years 1857-1874, excepting the 1866-1867 school year. These reports contain censuses of Wesleyan's student body, including lists of students that have died or taken seriously ill during the school year. They also include Cummings' recommendation that women be admitted into Wesleyan and his suggestions for allocation of funds, most prominently with regards to building and maintaining a library. The collection also contains Cummings' correspondence, including with Julia Olin and W.O. Atwater (primarily regarding securing Atwater's employment), as well as Cummings' official acceptance of the position as president at Wesleyan University. Also included are several articles by Cummings, a petition against his resignation from the professorship, and his wife D.S. Cummings' correspondence.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Cummings, Joseph, 1817-1890.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Presidents.; Olin, Julia M. (Julia Matilda), 1814-1879.; Atwater, W. O. (Wilbur Olin), 1844-1907.; Cummings, Deborah S.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Administration.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Annual Reports on Wesleyan University by Joseph Cummings
    - 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1860-1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1865-1866 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1867-1868 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1869-1870 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1870-1871 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1873-1874 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Typed transcripts of annual reports (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Library-related papers, 1867-1870 (Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1851-1867 and transcripts (Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1873-1876 and transcripts (Folder 20)
  - Newspaper articles and petition, 1875-1878 (Folder 21)
  - Notes and correspondence from Deborah S. Cummings, circa 1890-1899 (Folder 21)